Let me tell you a story.
دعني أخبركم بقصة.
It goes back 200 million years.
تعود إلى 200 مليون سنة.
It's a story of the neocortex,
إنها قصة القشرة المخية الحديثة،
which means "new rind."
والتى تعنى "قشرة جديدة".
So in these early mammals,
إذا فى هذه الثدييات السالفة،
because only mammals have a neocortex,
لأن الثديات فقط هي التي تتوفر على قشرة مخية حديثة،
rodent-like creatures.
مخلوقات كالقوارض.
It was the size of a postage stamp and just as thin,
كانت بحجم طابع البريد ونحيفة مثله،
and was a thin covering around
وكان هناك غطاء نحيف حول
their walnut-sized brain,
دماغها الذي هو بحجم جوز عين الجمل،
but it was capable of a new type of thinking.
ولكن كانت قادرة على نوع جديد من التفكير.
Rather than the fixed behaviors
بدلاً من السلوكيات الثابتة
that non-mammalian animals have,
التى تمتلكها الحيوانات الغير ثدية العادية،
it could invent new behaviors.
كانت قادرة على اختراع سلوكيات جديدة.
So a mouse is escaping a predator,
كهروب فأر من مفترس،
its path is blocked,
طريقه مسدود،
it'll try to invent a new solution.
سيحاول اختراع حل جديد.
That may work, it may not,
الذى يمكن أن يفلح، أو لا،
but if it does, it will remember that
ولكن إذا أفلح، سيتذكره
and have a new behavior,
ويمتلك سلوكا جديدا،
and that can actually spread virally
وهذا يمكن أن ينتشر كالفيروس
through the rest of the community.
إلى باقي المجموعة.
Another mouse watching this could say,
فأر آخر يشاهد الأتي يمكن أن يقول،
"Hey, that was pretty clever, going around that rock,"
"هذا فى قمة الذكاء، أن تمشى حول هذه الصخرة،"
and it could adopt a new behavior as well.
ويمكن أن يتخذ سلوك جديد أيضًا.
Non-mammalian animals
الحيوانات الغير ثدية
couldn't do any of those things.
لم تتمكن من فعل أي من هذه الأشياء.
They had fixed behaviors.
كانوا يمتلكون سلوكيات ثابتة.
Now they could learn a new behavior
حاليًا يمكنهم تعلم سلوك جديد
but not in the course of one lifetime.
ولكن ليس على مدى حياة واحدة.
In the course of maybe a thousand lifetimes,
ربما على امتداد آلاف الحيوات،
it could evolve a new fixed behavior.
يمكنهم تطوير سلوك ثابت جديد.
That was perfectly okay 200 million years ago.
كان هذا على نحو تام جيدا قبل 200 مليون سنة.
The environment changed very slowly.
البيئة تغيرت ببطىء شديد.
It could take 10,000 years for there to be
يمكنها أخذ 10 ألاف سنة ليكون هناك
a significant environmental change,
تغير بيئي ملحوظ،
and during that period of time
وخلال هذه الفترة من الزمن
it would evolve a new behavior.
تكون قد طورت سلوكا جديدا.
Now that went along fine,
الآن هذا مضى جيدا،
but then something happened.
ولكن شىء حدث.
Sixty-five million years ago,
قبل 65 مليون سنة،
there was a sudden, violent change to the environment.
كان هناك تغير فجائي وعنيف على البيئة.
We call it the Cretaceous extinction event.
نحن نسميه واقعة الانقراض الطباشيري.
That's when the dinosaurs went extinct,
كان هذا عندما انقرضت الديناصورات،
that's when 75 percent of the
كان هذا عندما تعرضت 75 فى المئة من ال
animal and plant species went extinct,
الحيوانات والنباتات للانقراض،
and that's when mammals
وآنذاك تفوقت الثدييات
overtook their ecological niche,
على ركنها البيئي،
and to anthropomorphize, biological evolution said,
وعلى سبيل التجسيم، قال التطور البيولوجي،
"Hmm, this neocortex is pretty good stuff,"
"ممم، هذه القشرة المخية الحديثة شىء جيد،"
and it began to grow it.
وبدأ فى إنمائها.
And mammals got bigger,
وكبرت الثدييات،
their brains got bigger at an even faster pace,
وكبرت أدمغتها بنسبة أسرع،
and the neocortex got bigger even faster than that
والقشرة المخية الحديثة كبرت أسرع من هذا أيضًا
and developed these distinctive ridges and folds
واكتسبت هذه التلال والطيات المميزة
basically to increase its surface area.
فى الأساس لتنمية مساحتها السطحية.
If you took the human neocortex
لو أخذت القشرة المخية الحديثة للانسان
and stretched it out,
ومططتها،
it's about the size of a table napkin,
هى بحجم يقارب مفرش الطاولة،
and it's still a thin structure.
وما زالت نحيفة البنية.
It's about the thickness of a table napkin.
هى بسماكة مفرش طاولة تقريبا.
But it has so many convolutions and ridges
ولكن لديها الكثير من التلافيف والتلال
it's now 80 percent of our brain,
هى تشكل حاليا 80 بالمئة من دماغنا،
and that's where we do our thinking,
وهذا حيث نقوم بالتفكير،
and it's the great sublimator.
وهو التسامى العظيم.
We still have that old brain
نحن ما زلنا نمتلك هذا الدماغ القديم
that provides our basic drives and motivations,
الذى يزودنا بمحركاتنا الأساسية والتحفيزات،
but I may have a drive for conquest,
ولكن ربما يمتلك محرك للاحتلال،
and that'll be sublimated by the neocortex
وهذا سيصعّد بالقشرة المخية الحديثة
into writing a poem or inventing an app
إلى كتابة قصيدة او اختراع تطبيق
or giving a TED Talk,
أو تقديم محادثة TED،
and it's really the neocortex that's where
وهذا حقًا مكمن القشرة المخية الحديثة، حيث
the action is.
تقع الأحداث.
Fifty years ago, I wrote a paper
قبل 50 سنة، كتبت ورقة بحثية
describing how I thought the brain worked,
أصف فيها كيف تخيلت عمل الدماغ،
and I described it as a series of modules.
ووصفته كسلسلة من الوحدات.
Each module could do things with a pattern.
كل وحدة يمكنها فعل أشياء بنمط.
It could learn a pattern. It could remember a pattern.
يمكنها التعلم نمط. يمكنها التذكر نمط.
It could implement a pattern.
يمكنها التطبيق نمط.
And these modules were organized in hierarchies,
وهذه الوحدات كانت منظمة فى تسلسلات هرمية،
and we created that hierarchy with our own thinking.
وألفنا هذا التسلسل الهرمى بطريقة تفكيرنا.
And there was actually very little to go on
وكان فى الحقيقة هناك قليل جدا للاعتماد عليه
50 years ago.
قبل 50 سنة.
It led me to meet President Johnson.
قادتني لمقابلة الرئيس جونسون.
I've been thinking about this for 50 years,
كنت أفكر فى هذا لحوالى 50 سنة،
and a year and a half ago I came out with the book
وقبل سنة ونصف خرجت بهذا الكتاب
"How To Create A Mind,"
"كيف تخلق دماغا،"
which has the same thesis,
والذي يحتوى على نفس الفرضية،
but now there's a plethora of evidence.
ولكن حاليا هناك وفرة من الأدلة.
The amount of data we're getting about the brain
وكمية المعلومات التى نحصل عليها عن الدماغ
from neuroscience is doubling every year.
من علم الأعصاب تتضاعف كل سنة.
Spatial resolution of brainscanning of all types
دقة كل أنواع فحص الدماغ الدقيق
is doubling every year.
تتضاعف كل سنة.
We can now see inside a living brain
يمكننا الآن أن نرى داخل دماغ حي
and see individual interneural connections
ونرى روابط خلية بينية فردية
connecting in real time, firing in real time.
متواصلة فى أوقات حقيقة، ترسل إشارات فى أوقات حقيقة.
We can see your brain create your thoughts.
يمكننا أن نرى دماغك يخلق أفكارك.
We can see your thoughts create your brain,
يمكننا أن نرى أفكارك تخلق دماغك،
which is really key to how it works.
والذى هو فى الحقيقة مفتاح لكيف يعمل.
So let me describe briefly how it works.
فدعني أشرح باختصار كيف يعمل.
I've actually counted these modules.
أنا فى الحقيقة عددت هذه الوحدات.
We have about 300 million of them,
نمتلك حوالى 300 مليون منها،
and we create them in these hierarchies.
ونخلقها فى هذه التسلسلات الهرمية.
I'll give you a simple example.
سوف أعطي لك مثالا مبسطا.
I've got a bunch of modules
أمتلك حزمة وحدات
that can recognize the crossbar to a capital A,
يمكنها ملاحظة العارضة لحرف الA الكبير،
and that's all they care about.
وهذا كل ما تهتم به.
A beautiful song can play,
أغنية جميلة يمكن أن تعزف،
a pretty girl could walk by,
فتاة جميلة تسير،
they don't care, but they see a crossbar to a capital A,
لا تكترث لذلك، ولكن ترى عارضة الحرف الكبير A،
they get very excited and they say "crossbar,"
فتتحمس وتقول "عارضة،"
and they put out a high probability
وتضع نسبية كبيرة
on their output axon.
على نتاج محورهم العصبي.
That goes to the next level,
هذا يذهب للمرحلة التالية،
and these layers are organized in conceptual levels.
وهذه الطبقات منظمة فى مراحل مفاهيمية.
Each is more abstract than the next one,
كل واحدة ملخصة أكثر من التالية،
so the next one might say "capital A."
فالتالية يمكن أن تقول "حرف الA الكبير."
That goes up to a higher level that might say "Apple."
هذا يذهب إلى مرحلة أعلى التى يمكن أن تقول "تفاحة."
Information flows down also.
المعلومات تنحدر أيضًا.
If the apple recognizer has seen A-P-P-L,
إن رأى المتعرف على "التفاحة" A-P-P-L،
it'll think to itself, "Hmm, I think an E is probably likely,"
سيفكر فى نفسه، "امم، أعتقد أن الE يكاد أن يكون،"
and it'll send a signal down to all the E recognizers
وسترسل إشارة نزولا لكل المتعرفين على الE
saying, "Be on the lookout for an E,
يقول, "احترس من الE،
I think one might be coming."
أعتقد أن واحدة قد تأتي."
The E recognizers will lower their threshold
المتعرفون على الE سيقللون المسموح
and they see some sloppy thing, could be an E.
ويروا شىئا منحدرا، يمكن أن يكون E.
Ordinarily you wouldn't think so,
غالبًا لن تفكر هكذا،
but we're expecting an E, it's good enough,
ولكن نحن نتوقع E، هذا جيد كفاية،
and yeah, I've seen an E, and then apple says,
ونعم، لقد رأيت E، وثم تقول التفاحة،
"Yeah, I've seen an Apple."
"نعم, لقد رأيت تفاحة."
Go up another five levels,
اصعد 5 مراحل أخرى،
and you're now at a pretty high level
وأنت الأن عند مرحلة عالية
of this hierarchy,
من هذا التسلسل الهرمي،
and stretch down into the different senses,
وامتد نزولا للأحاسيس المختلفة،
and you may have a module that sees a certain fabric,
ويمكن أن تمتلك وحدة ترى نسيجا معينا،
hears a certain voice quality, smells a certain perfume,
تسمع خامة صوت معينة، تشم عطرا معينا،
and will say, "My wife has entered the room."
وتقول، "زوجتى دخلت الغرفة."
Go up another 10 levels, and now you're at
اصعد 10 مراحل أخرى، والآن أنت عند
a very high level.
مرحلة عالية جدا.
You're probably in the frontal cortex,
أنت فى الغالب عند القشرة الأمامية،
and you'll have modules that say, "That was ironic.
وسيكون لديك وحدات تقول، "كان هذا ساخرا.
That's funny. She's pretty."
هذا مضحك. هى جميلة."
You might think that those are more sophisticated,
يمكن أن تعتقد أن أولئك أكثر تعقيدًا،
but actually what's more complicated
ولكن فى الحقيقة الأكثر تعقيدًا
is the hierarchy beneath them.
هو التسلسل الهرمى أدناهم.
There was a 16-year-old girl, she had brain surgery,
كان هناك فتاة لديها 16 عاما، أجرت جراحة دماغية،
and she was conscious because the surgeons
وكانت فى وعيها لأن الجراحين
wanted to talk to her.
كانوا فى حاجة للتحدث معها.
You can do that because there's no pain receptors
يمكنك فعل هذا لأنه لا توجد مستقبلات للألم
in the brain.
فى الدماغ.
And whenever they stimulated particular,
وحين نشطوا،
very small points on her neocortex,
نقطة صغيرة جدًا معينة على قشرتها المخية الجديدة،
shown here in red, she would laugh.
متضحة هنا بالأحمر، كانت تضحك.
So at first they thought they were triggering
فى الأول ظنوا أنهم يثيرون
some kind of laugh reflex,
نوعا ما من الضحك المنعكس،
but no, they quickly realized they had found
ولكن لا، بسرعة أدركوا أنهم وجدوا
the points in her neocortex that detect humor,
النقاط فى قشرتها المخية الحديثة التى تكتشف الفكاهة،
and she just found everything hilarious
ووجدت كل شيء مضحكا
whenever they stimulated these points.
كلما حفزوا هذه النقاط.
"You guys are so funny just standing around,"
"أيها الرجال إنكم مضحكون واقفون بالقرب،"
was the typical comment,
كان التعليق النموذجي،
and they weren't funny,
ولم يكونوا مضحكين،
not while doing surgery.
ليس فى قت إجراء الجراحة.
So how are we doing today?
أين نحن اليوم؟
Well, computers are actually beginning to master
حسنا، الحواسيب الآلية فى بداية إتقان
human language with techniques
لغة الإنسان بأساليب
that are similar to the neocortex.
تتشابه مع القشرة المخية الحديثة.
I actually described the algorithm,
أنا فى الحقيقة وصفت الخوارزمية،
which is similar to something called
التى تتماثل مع شىء إسمه
a hierarchical hidden Markov model,
موديل ماركوف الهرمى المخبأ،
something I've worked on since the '90s.
شيء عملت عليه من التسعينات.
"Jeopardy" is a very broad natural language game,
"جيباردى" هى لعبة لغة طبيعية متوسعة،
and Watson got a higher score
وواتسن حصل على مجموع أعلى
than the best two players combined.
من أفضل لاعبين مندمجين.
It got this query correct:
حصلت على هذه المسألة صحيحة:
"A long, tiresome speech
"خطاب شاق، طويل
delivered by a frothy pie topping,"
منقول بطبقة علوية ذو رغوة،"
and it quickly responded, "What is a meringue harangue?"
وتفاعلت بسرعة، "ما هو خطب المارنغ؟"
And Jennings and the other guy didn't get that.
و جينينجس والرجل الآخر لم يفهموا ذلك.
It's a pretty sophisticated example of
هو مثال معقد من
computers actually understanding human language,
الحواسيب الآلية والتي في الحقيقة تفهم لغة الإنسان،
and it actually got its knowledge by reading
وفي الحقيقة حصلت على معرفتها من قراءة
Wikipedia and several other encyclopedias.
ويكيبيديا وبعض الموسوعات الأخرى.
Five to 10 years from now,
بعد 5 إلى 10 سنين من الآن،
search engines will actually be based on
ستكون المحركات البحثية فى الحقيقة مبنية على
not just looking for combinations of words and links
ليس فقط البحث عن كلمات مركبة وروابط
but actually understanding,
ولكن فى الحقيقة على فهم،
reading for understanding the billions of pages
وقراءة الملايير من الصفحات
on the web and in books.
على الشبكة العنكبوتية وفى الكتب.
So you'll be walking along, and Google will pop up
سوف تكون تسير، وجوجل سيظهر
and say, "You know, Mary, you expressed concern
و يقول، "تعرفين يا ماري، لقد عبرتي لي عن اهتمامك
to me a month ago that your glutathione supplement
قبل شهر مضى عن مكمل الجلوتاثيون
wasn't getting past the blood-brain barrier.
لم يكن يعبر خلال حاجز دم المخ.
Well, new research just came out 13 seconds ago
حسنًا، بحث جديد ظهر قبل 13 ثانية
that shows a whole new approach to that
يوضح مقاربة جديدة كليًا لهذا
and a new way to take glutathione.
وطريقة جديدة لأخذ الجلوتاثيون.
Let me summarize it for you."
دعيني ألخصها لك."
Twenty years from now, we'll have nanobots,
20 سنة من الآن، سنمتلك روبوتاتٍ صغيرة،
because another exponential trend
لأن إتجاها أسيا أخر
is the shrinking of technology.
هو تقلص التكنولوجيا.
They'll go into our brain
سيذهبون إلى داخل أدمغتنا
through the capillaries
خلال الشعيرات الدموية
and basically connect our neocortex
ويقومون في الأساس بربط قشرتنا المخية الحديثة
to a synthetic neocortex in the cloud
بقشرة مخية حديثة صناعية في السحاب
providing an extension of our neocortex.
توفر تمديد لقشرتنا المخية الحديثة.
Now today, I mean,
الآن، وأعني اليوم،
you have a computer in your phone,
تمتلك حاسوبا في هاتفك،
but if you need 10,000 computers for a few seconds
ولكن لو تحتاج الى 10,000 كمبيوتر لثوانٍ معدودة
to do a complex search,
لعمل بحث معقد،
you can access that for a second or two in the cloud.
يمكنك الوصول إليه لثانية أو ثانيتين فى السحابة.
In the 2030s, if you need some extra neocortex,
فى الثلاثينيات من هذا القرن ، لو أنت بحاجة إلى بعض القشر المخية الحديثة الإضافية،
you'll be able to connect to that in the cloud
ستتمكن من الإتصال بها فى السحاب
directly from your brain.
مباشرة من مخك.
So I'm walking along and I say,
إذا أكون ماشيا فأقول،
"Oh, there's Chris Anderson.
"ا هو كريس أندرسون.
He's coming my way.
إنه قادم فى طريقي.
I'd better think of something clever to say.
من الأفضل أن أفكر فى شيء ذكي لقوله.
I've got three seconds.
لدي ثلاث ثوانٍ.
My 300 million modules in my neocortex
ال300 مليون وحدة التي أمتلكها فى قشرتي المخية الحديثة
isn't going to cut it.
لن تكون كافية.
I need a billion more."
أحتاج إلى مليار أكثر."
I'll be able to access that in the cloud.
سأتمكن من الوصول إليها فى السحاب.
And our thinking, then, will be a hybrid
وتفكيرنا، بعدها، سيكون هجينا
of biological and non-biological thinking,
من التفكير البيولوجي والغير بيلوجي،
but the non-biological portion
ولكن الجزء الغير بيولوجي
is subject to my law of accelerating returns.
يتعلق بقانوني لتسريع العوائد.
It will grow exponentially.
ستكبر أضعافًا مضاعفة.
And remember what happens
وهل تتذكر ماذا حدث
the last time we expanded our neocortex?
آخر مرة كبرنا فيها قشرتنا المخية الحديثة؟
That was two million years ago
كان هذا منذ مليوني سنة
when we became humanoids
عندما أصبحنا كائنات تشبه الحيوانات
and developed these large foreheads.
وطورنا هذه الجباه الكبيرة.
Other primates have a slanted brow.
قرود أخرى لديها جبين مائلة.
They don't have the frontal cortex.
ليس لديهم القشرة الأمامية.
But the frontal cortex is not really qualitatively different.
ولكن القشرة الأمامية ليست مختلفة حقًا نوعيًا.
It's a quantitative expansion of neocortex,
هى تضخم كمي للقشرة المخية الحديثة،
but that additional quantity of thinking
ولكن هذه الكمية الإضافية فى التفكير
was the enabling factor for us to take
كانت العامل المؤهل لنا لأخذ
a qualitative leap and invent language
طفرة نوعية واختراع اللغة
and art and science and technology
والفن والعلوم والتكنولوجيا
and TED conferences.
ومؤتمرات TED.
No other species has done that.
لا يوجد نوع فعل ذلك.
And so, over the next few decades,
ولذلك، خلال العقود القليلة القادمة،
we're going to do it again.
سنقوم بها مجددا.
We're going to again expand our neocortex,
سنقوم مجددًا بتوسيع قشرتنا المخية الحديثة،
only this time we won't be limited
فقط هذه المرة لن نقتصر
by a fixed architecture of enclosure.
على تصميم هندسي سياجي معين.
It'll be expanded without limit.
سوف تتوسع بلا حدود.
That additional quantity will again
هذه الكمية الزائدة سوف
be the enabling factor for another qualitative leap
تكون مجددا العامل الممكّن لطفرة نوعية أخرى
in culture and technology.
فى الثقافة والتكنولوجيا.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)